<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Copyright (c) 2010, 2018 Oracle and/or its affiliates. All rights reserved.

    This program and the accompanying materials are made available under the
    terms of the Eclipse Distribution License v. 1.0, which is available at
    http://www.eclipse.org/org/documents/edl-v10.php.

    SPDX-License-Identifier: BSD-3-Clause

-->

<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM "metro.ent">
%ents;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="bootstrap_config" xml:lang="en"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Bootstrapping and Configuration</title>

    <section xml:id="bootstrap_config-server_endpoint">
        <title>What is a Server-Side Endpoint?</title>

        <para>Web services expose one or more endpoints to which messages can
        be sent. A web service endpoint is an entity, processor, or resource
        that can be referenced and to which web services messages can be
        addressed. Endpoint references convey the information needed to
        address a web service endpoint. Clients need to know this information
        before they can access a service.</para>

        <para>Typically, web services package endpoint descriptions and use a
        WSDL file to share these descriptions with clients. Clients use the
        web service endpoint description to generate code that can send SOAP
        messages to and receive SOAP messages from the web service
        endpoint.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="bootstrap_config-client_from_wsdl">
        <title>Creating a Client from WSDL</title>

        <para>To create a web service client that can access and consume a web
        service provider, you must obtain the information that defines the
        interoperability requirements of the web service provider. Providers
        make this information available by means of WSDL files. WSDL files may
        be made available in service registries or published on the Internet
        using a URL (or both). You can use a web browser or NetBeans IDE to
        obtain WSDL files.</para>

        <para>A WSDL file contains descriptions of the following:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Network services</emphasis>: The description
                includes the name of the service, the location of the service,
                and ways to communicate with the service, that is, what
                transport to use.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Web services policies</emphasis>: Policies
                express the capabilities, requirements, and general
                characteristics of a web service. Web service providers use
                policies to specify policy information in a standardized way.
                Policies convey conditions on interactions between two web
                service endpoints. Typically, the provider of a web service
                exposes a policy to convey conditions under which it provides
                the service. A requester (a client) might use the policy to
                decide whether or not to use the service.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Web Services Metadata Exchange (WS-MEX) is the protocol for
        requesting and transferring the WSDL from the provider to the client.
        This protocol is a bootstrap mechanism for communication.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="bootstrap_config-client_from_wsdl_examples">
        <title>Client From WSDL Examples</title>

        <para>The following sections, found in other chapters of this
        tutorial, explain how to create a client from a WSDL file using the
        example files in the tutorial bundle:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><xref
                linkend="wsit_example_with_nb-creating_wsit_client"
                xrefstyle="select:title" /> shows how to create a client from
                WSDL using a web container and the NetBeans IDE.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><xref linkend="ahigi" xrefstyle="select:title" /> shows
                how to create a client from WSDL using only a web
                container.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
